<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Prag-o-matic - 6hats</title><link href="http://www.duncan.dickinson.name/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://www.duncan.dickinson.name/feeds/6hats.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://www.duncan.dickinson.name/</id><updated>2014-12-12T07:00:00+10:00</updated><entry><title>Wear the hats every day (Part 3)</title><link href="http://www.duncan.dickinson.name/2014/12/wear-hats-every-day-part-3.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2014-12-12T07:00:00+10:00</published><updated>2014-12-12T07:00:00+10:00</updated><author><name>Duncan</name></author><id>tag:www.duncan.dickinson.name,2014-12-12:/2014/12/wear-hats-every-day-part-3.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This is Part 3 of a 3-part series.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Often when I'm working&amp;nbsp; with teams and individuals I don't formally use the Six Thinking Hats. In fact, I rarely make it explicit that this is guiding the discussion. As a project manager or business analyst I use the hats to guide …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This is Part 3 of a 3-part series.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Often when I'm working&amp;nbsp; with teams and individuals I don't formally use the Six Thinking Hats. In fact, I rarely make it explicit that this is guiding the discussion. As a project manager or business analyst I use the hats to guide the discussion, especially to dig deeper into statements. For example, I might be tasked with analysing a process as-is and work towards the future process. The naive way to do this is to ask a group to describe their process/system and then how they feel it could be improved. This is suboptimal as it can gloss over deeper issues and also puts people on the spot. Instead, I might follow a process such as the one that follows.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s quickly remind ourselves of the hats:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;White hat&lt;/strong&gt;: The white hat focuses on facts.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Red hat&lt;/strong&gt;: The red hat focuses on feelings&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Black hat&lt;/strong&gt;: The black hat focuses on caution&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Yellow hat&lt;/strong&gt;: The yellow hat focuses on optimism&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Green hat&lt;/strong&gt;: The green hat focuses on being creative&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Blue hat&lt;/strong&gt;: The blue hat focuses on the thinking process&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="stage-1-find-out-what-is"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Stage 1 - Find out what is&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I review the project brief and any existing process documentation (White Hat) or ask a team member to individually describe it to me. I may also look into related policies and laws to determine the broader organisational context.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="stage-2-understand-why-it-is"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Stage 2 - Understand why it is&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I then meet with the team(s) involved and go through the process to determine if the documentation matches reality (White hat). This could run as a large workshop or individual small groups depending on how I feel I'd get the best results (Blue hat). The workshop may use the review of the existing process as its spine but the discussion will lead in various directions, sometimes prompted by me or initiated by participants:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol class="arabic simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The review may draw out disconnects between the &amp;quot;theory&amp;quot; and the &amp;quot;reality&amp;quot; and the Red hat can help here if parts of the process are avoided or ignored - it's important to find out if people avoid something due to frustration.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Black hat may also be useful here if people raise concerns about the current process. Perhaps things get through that shouldn't or parts of the process are rushed due to time expectations. These can be cautionary tales that could be handled in the new process.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="stage-3-consider-the-path-ahead"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Stage 3 - Consider the path ahead&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I then take a break - maybe for a day or more. This is Blue hat time - a chance to review my findings, reflect on the various parties, perhaps seek clarification on various elements, speak to management about progress, and even prepare some discussion materials such as flow charts. This helps me work out my next focus: improving the process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Knowing what constitutes &amp;quot;improving&amp;quot; is critical. Does the organisation want to save money, improve compliance, reduce delays etc? Perhaps the organisation isn't sure what's happening &amp;quot;on the ground&amp;quot; and is seeking clarity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is also a time to classify the type of process or system you're looking at. If you're working in a highly regulated environment then a new process may be predetermined and focus is on how to gain efficiencies. At the other end of the spectrum you may be in a complex environment that requires you to navigate personal, structural, technical and even social challenges. Knowing the lay of the land before embarking on a journey can provide some &amp;quot;travel insurance&amp;quot;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's important to also consider the option of not changing anything - the existing system/process may operate effectively or a new system may cost more than any potential gains. This is a &amp;quot;null hypothesis&amp;quot; that predicts that nothing will be significantly changed by action.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="stage-4-start-the-journey"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Stage 4 - Start the journey&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At this point the road will diverge based on your Blue hat thinking and planning. I've rarely found projects match up in such a way that I can just repeat what I'd done earlier - this is why experience, agility and good humour are perhaps the most important skills for project managers and business analysts. Rather than just say &amp;quot;This stage depends on many things&amp;quot;, I'll mention some common schemes I employ:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The project may allow for a lot of creative (Green hat) thinking and this could let teams work on prototypes and then use the White, Red, Black and Yellow hats to compare and contrast each solution to determine the optimal one.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A large stuctural change in an organisation or the industry might be in play and require a lot of Red hat discussions to determine the impact on the people involved. The Yellow hat and the Black hat can then help guide and progress thinking - with the Green hat letting people build new ideas that grow Yellow hat ideas and shrink Black hat issues.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Unfortunately the technical solution may have already been selected in a &amp;quot;cart before the horse&amp;quot; approach. In this case you have a &amp;quot;fixed cost&amp;quot; and then use the hats to determine the most effective outcome.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;nbsp;The time or budget available for the project may be less than optimal. In this case the White hat helps you focus on what you know and manage project scope. The Yellow and Green hats can help find opportunities within the limitations and the Black hat helps manage scope.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lastly, never be afraid to go back to the earlier stages to check and verify your progress.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="conclusion"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That wraps up the 3-part introduction to how I approach the 6 Thinking Hats in my work. Like any thinking skill using the 6 Hats is something you have to do over time so as to find how it best works for you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;® Six Thinking Hats is a registered trademark of Edward de Bono&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content><category term="6hats"></category><category term="problem solving"></category><category term="thinking"></category></entry><entry><title>Put on a hat when asking questions (Part 2)</title><link href="http://www.duncan.dickinson.name/2014/12/put-on-hat-when-asking-questions-part-2.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2014-12-05T07:00:00+10:00</published><updated>2014-12-05T07:00:00+10:00</updated><author><name>Duncan</name></author><id>tag:www.duncan.dickinson.name,2014-12-05:/2014/12/put-on-hat-when-asking-questions-part-2.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This is Part 2 of a 3-part series.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can work through each of the hats in any order but it’s more effective when two hats pair up. This isn’t to play each off each other or fall into debate (something your use of the hats is trying …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This is Part 2 of a 3-part series.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can work through each of the hats in any order but it’s more effective when two hats pair up. This isn’t to play each off each other or fall into debate (something your use of the hats is trying to avoid). Rather, the paired hats work well together and you may run the discussion with one hat then review with its pair.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The pairing also helps manage the discussion by:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol class="arabic simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Separating Black and Red hat thinking - this is helpful as many people have decided (or been told) that Black hat thinking is negative thinking. A statement such as “This won’t work as the network team don’t get it” is Red hat thinking and not Black hat. A statement such as “The network team may not like this as it opens up the system too much” is Black hat as it raises a concern that needs to be looked into.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Pairing the White and Red hat so as to help in determining if a statement of discussion is reflecting a fact or a feeling. These can sometimes be difficult to discern so having them in close proximity can help guide us in clarifying what’s being put forward.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s quickly remind ourselves of the hats:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;White hat&lt;/strong&gt;: The white hat focuses on facts.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Red hat&lt;/strong&gt;: The red hat focuses on feelings&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Black hat&lt;/strong&gt;: The black hat focuses on caution&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Yellow hat&lt;/strong&gt;: The yellow hat focuses on optimism&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Green hat&lt;/strong&gt;: The green hat focuses on being creative&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Blue hat&lt;/strong&gt;: The blue hat focuses on the thinking process&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So let’s look at the 3 pairings that work well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="white-and-red"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;White and red&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This explores facts and feelings and can highlight areas such as processes that aren’t working.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, an organisation may provide an online service that imposes a process on users that reflects the organisational structure very closely. Discussions with users may reveal that, whilst they can use the system, they find the process rather obscure as they’re not part of your organisation. This leads to frustration (expressed with the Red hat) that can help refine the process (White hat).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When looking at new systems being introduced within an organisation, the White and Red hats can help with change management. The new system may introduce a need for re-skilling and new processes and it’s important to determine people how they feel about this and how they can be encouraged to engage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="black-and-yellow"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Black and yellow&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;System security is a great area for the Black and Yellow hats to pair up. It often feels like developers wear yellow hats (“this great new system really helps us analyse our customer needs”) but the systems administrators wear black hats (“this system looks like it opens up too much information”).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Both statements are important to analyse and having both developers and sys admins wear the Black and Yellow hats gives them the opportunity to share their understanding and can really help a DevOps approach.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="green-and-blue"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Green and blue&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There’s an increasing amount of literature around building creativity in organisations and good use of the Blue hat to guide and encourage thinking, rather than debate, can help to tap the knowledge and skills of everyone involved.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Blue hat helps call back the team when they’re deep in Green hat territory. It’s important to keep an eye on requirements (White hat), possible areas of concern (Black hat) etc but it’s also important not to keep interjecting or you risk breaking a useful chain of thought.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The pairings listed above provide a handy guide to working through the thinking process but there are some areas for caution so always have the Blue hat ready:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Black hat focuses on caution and isn’t a whinge-fest. It’s important to let people express optimistic views without being constantly rained on by someone who (proudly) calls themselves a “Black hat thinker” - they’re more likely to be expressing a Red hat thought. I like to start with the Yellow hat and see what people like then start to explore areas that need a critical eye. The goal is not to be all sunshine and lollipops - it’s to develop an effective solution.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Creativity (Green hat) is important and can help an organisation become a leader in their market. However, few projects are a completely blank slate so it’s important to use the Blue hat to make sure that the team references other hats and can justify their actions - management is more likely to support something “out of the box” if you can explain it fully.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Whilst the White hat focuses on facts, the “truth” can be a fickle and personal thing. Sifting and sorting Yellow and White hat thinking can be tricky, especially when you’re looking at complex problems.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Establishing a common language/definition may be very useful here so that statements can be more quantifiable. For example “improved student outcomes” will have a large range of meaning depending on if you’re talking to: students, teachers, or administration&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Even legislation (law) may not be easily described as “fact” - especially if it hasn’t been tested. Instead of saying something like “raw data cannot be copyrighted” you may have to settle on a statement such as “raw data is unlikely to pass the 'sweat of the brow' provision of copyright law”. The more definite you can be with your facts, the easier they are to use when referring to them.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Some people like to use statement prefixes such as “It’s well-known that…” and “I think we all agree that…” to enforce their point and knowingly or to (perhaps unknowingly) quiet most dissent. It’s important to check across that group if it is indeed a fact (White hat) or a feeling (Red hat). Both are important so don’t dismiss the statement - it needs to be categorised and noted - throwing it away is likely to motivate the statement’s originator to try to undermine the discussion.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the next (and final) instalment I’ll offer an example of how I use the Six Thinking Hats in my work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;® Six Thinking Hats is a registered trademark of Edward de Bono&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content><category term="6hats"></category><category term="problem solving"></category><category term="thinking"></category></entry><entry><title>Try on the thinking hats (Part 1)</title><link href="http://www.duncan.dickinson.name/2014/11/try-on-thinking-hats-part-1.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2014-11-30T12:32:00+10:00</published><updated>2014-11-30T12:32:00+10:00</updated><author><name>Duncan</name></author><id>tag:www.duncan.dickinson.name,2014-11-30:/2014/11/try-on-thinking-hats-part-1.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Instead of judging our way forward, we need to design our way forward. We need to be thinking 'what can be', not just about 'what is'&lt;/em&gt; - Edward de Bono&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This is Part 1 of a 3-part series.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After several years of working long hours as a programmer I went into …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Instead of judging our way forward, we need to design our way forward. We need to be thinking 'what can be', not just about 'what is'&lt;/em&gt; - Edward de Bono&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This is Part 1 of a 3-part series.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After several years of working long hours as a programmer I went into teaching - it was my interest in learning and problem solving that motivated me. As developers and development teams we engage in learning throughout our careers but primarily in terms of &amp;quot;technical skills&amp;quot; rather than &amp;quot;meta skills&amp;quot;. These meta skills focus on areas such as how we learn and how we engage others to help us achieve goals. I've worked with many people that I would class as excellent developers. These people can solve coding problems quickly and elegantly but I've noticed that they often do so with blinkers on. As teams engage in agile approaches to projects it is important that they engage more closely in understanding the environment in which they are working.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whilst studying and then working as a teacher, the skills around thinking and the area of&amp;nbsp;&lt;em&gt;metacognition&lt;/em&gt; became a primary interest to me. One well-known strategy for guiding thinking is Edward de Bono's &amp;quot;Six Thinking Hats&amp;quot; - first published in 1985. The six hats provide an enduring method for framing how teams can examine problems and seek effective solutions:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;White hat&lt;/strong&gt;: The white hat focuses on facts.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Red hat&lt;/strong&gt;: The red hat focuses on feelings&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;dl class="first docutils"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Black hat&lt;/strong&gt;: The black hat focuses on caution&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;&lt;ul class="first last"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Be careful with the term &amp;quot;black hat&amp;quot; as it is often aligned with negativity&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Yellow hat&lt;/strong&gt;: The yellow hat focuses on optimism&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Green hat&lt;/strong&gt;: The green hat focuses on being creative&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Blue hat&lt;/strong&gt;: The blue hat focuses on the thinking process.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some people react badly to the six hats approach but it's important to understand what's causing this. Here are a few examples worth considering:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;quot;This is just new age mumbo jumbo&amp;quot;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Some people really like to argue and anything that sounds like they won't be able to push their idea threatens them. The key risk with these people is that they believe the loudest argument is the strongest argument. Encourage these people to engage but be definite in adhering to the process - calling out when they're trying to dominate.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;quot;This will take too long&amp;quot;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Some people feel that it's quicker to &amp;quot;work out the answer and go for it&amp;quot;. Unfortunately this is often a form of &amp;quot;shallow&amp;quot; problem solving - they haven't really worked out a good answer and, usually, they've focussed on the technical aspect and not the whole issue. I've found that the first answer, once put under scrutiny, starts to fall apart quickly and, if the team had started development, a large amount of time is wasted in code.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The best approach to handling criticisms is confidence. Make sure that you are comfortable with the six hats and that you keep the group on task. Don't be afraid to cancel the session if a participant just won't cooperate - walk away, put on your blue hat, reflect and look at approaching from a different angle. Avoid the following to help retain purpose:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Don't make people wear a hat as it can reduce the session into a side show.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Don't allocate each person a specific hat for the session as the group should be working with the same hat at any one time.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Stay &amp;quot;on hat&amp;quot; by parking comments that fall under a different hat. Note the point on a whiteboard and direct the group back to the current hat.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Monitor the highly assertive group members. Not everyone likes to proactively put ideas forward but, assuming you have a good team, encouraging the whole team can lead to solutions that the loud mouths never thought of.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Blue hat is very useful when planning a session with an individual or a team. You don't have to use all of the hats in every session, indeed it can be very useful to focus on a single hat.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One example is when reviewing a workflow: the White hat is really useful as you just want to know what the steps are and who carries them out - later on you could arrange a session that uses other hats to focus on issues such as problems with the workflow (Black hat) or improvements to the workflow (Green hat).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the next article I'll look at how you can use the hats in a pairing arrangement to help you to direct your questioning during analysis work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="further-reading"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Further reading&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.penguin.com.au/products/9780141037554/six-thinking-hats-popular-penguins"&gt;Six Thinking Hats&lt;/a&gt; by Edward de Bono&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;® Six Thinking Hats is a registered trademark of Edward de Bono&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content><category term="6hats"></category><category term="problem solving"></category><category term="thinking"></category></entry></feed>